Hi, welcome to Yoga
for neck and shoulders. My name
is Rosa and I will be guiding
you through this practice. Our
focus today will be on the neck
and shoulder area where we want
to prevent pain or release
discomfort if you're already
experiencing it. And we're going
to work against the posture that
so many of us have when we sit
and work with our smartphones or
computers, so hunching forward,
and instead we want to lift up
an elevate through the spine,
especially through the neck,
rolling the shoulders back and
down and away from each other.
Let's combine that with our
breath and a little shoulder
rotation. So on your next
inhale, reach your shoulders up
to your ears and as you hunched
forward through the upper back
and exhaling slide your shoulder
blades back down and away from
each other. Inhale hunched
forward, shoulders to ears.
Exhale, shoulders back down and
away from each other. Close your
eyes. Inhale forward, up. Exhale
back down and away from each
other. And then take another two
rounds on your own breathing
deeply and feeling into your
shoulders.
And then on your next inhale,
open your eyes and come into all
fours, your pelvis is right on
top of your knees here and your
knees or hips width apart. That
means you can fit two fists in
between your knees. Your hands
come down under your shoulders,
fingers spreading super wide,
middle fingers facing forward
and your core is engaged. And
breathe deeply here. So in yoga,
we have a lot of poses where we
put weight on our hands such as
all fours and plank and down dog
and later on arm imbalances. And
it is crucial to have a healthy
alignment in your shoulders for
all of these poses because if
you don't you risk wrecking your
neck over time. So please take a
look as I show you how to align
your shoulders. Instead of
rolling your upper arms inwards
and hunching forward as I'm
doing here. Roll your upper arms
outwards, the soft part of your
elbows face forward and smile at
whatever is ahead of you. The
same time your shoulders pulled
back into their sockets and your
heart is reaching forward.
Again, core is engaged. So let's
do that together. As you inhale,
roll your upper arms inwards
hunching forward
and exhale, roll them outwards
insides of elbows facing
forward. Once more, inhale
forward and exhale, hunching. So
feeding tension in the neck
here. And then again in how come
forward and stay activating your
shoulders. Take deep breaths,
breathing space between your
shoulder blades as you push the
knuckles of your hands down.
So now breathing into the space
that you created in your
shoulders and your neck and then
let's do a few rounds of cat and
cow here. So on your inhale
slowly roll up arching the spine
and exhale, roll down rounding
inhale starting at the bottom of
your spine one vertebra at a
time arching into Cow and exhale
vertebra by vertebra rounding
into cat pose. Take tumor rounds
on your own, really noticing
every single vertebra as you
move
and then I'll meet you in all
fours with a neutral spine.
Inhaling, press down through
your left hand, reach the right
arm up and exhale, rest the
right shoulder and your head
under your left shoulder.
Inhale, reach up through the
left hand placing your left hand
on your pelvis making sure that
your hips stay parallel to the
ground. And then you could stay
here this is a beautiful place
to stay or you could grab a hold
of your right thigh with your
left hand and breathe deeply
here using the shoulders away
from the ears, and as you
inhale, lift your left hand up
again. Exhale, rest your left
arm next to your left ear.
coming onto your left fingertips
fingers far ahead of you.
Shoulders stay away from your
ears. Inhale, pull your
shoulders away from your ears
again, and exhale, rest that
left shoulder on your right
upper arms, releasing the
weight. take three deep breaths,
core is strong.
And on your third, inhale, reach
up through your left hand and
exhale, place your left hand
down under your left shoulder
again. Inhale, reach up through
the right arm. And exhale, place
your right hand down under your
right shoulder.
On your inhale, reach out
through the left arm now and
exhaling release the left arm
down under your right shoulder
head rests on the ground and how
reach out through the right arm.
And exhale, resting your right
hand on your tailbone making
sure that the hips stay square.
Your core is engaged. You could
keep your hand on your tailbone
or grab a hold of that left
thigh. And again, deep breaths
here. On your next inhale,
release your right hand and rest
your right arm next to your
right ear. coming onto your
fingertips, making a spider hand
with that right hand. Inhale,
pull your shoulders away from
your ears. And then exhale, rest
that right shoulder on your left
upper arm.
Deep breaths and inhale, reach
up through the right arm again.
And as you exhale, press your
right hand down under your right
shoulder.
pose here. So your knees are as
wide as the mat and your big
toes touch. You're going to bend
your elbows and rest your hands
in prayer pose thumbs on your
neck. You don't know what I'm
talking about. Just take a look
I'm demonstrating. And then
release your head soften your
jaw and breathe deeply. From
here, begin to lock your hands
as far forward as possible.
Pressing your hands down
shoulder width apart your
shoulder stay away from your
ears. And then tuck your toes
bring your knees hips width feet
or hips width engage through
your core and pull your seat up
as you press your hands down
arriving in downward dog.
Inhale, pull your shoulders away
from your ears. And exhale, let
your head hang. Now on your
inhale, start walking your feet
to your hands folding over bent
knees once you're there. Your
feet or hips width apart here
and there's a two fist distance
between your feet and your head
is heavy. And then Interlace
your fingers behind your back
and on your inhale. Pull your
hands forward and up towards the
ceiling. And then exhaling let
them go towards the ground.
engaged with the belly. Shift
your weight further into the toe
side of your feet and take deep
breaths
then on your next exhale,
release your hands and place
your left hand on the ground of
foot length ahead and in between
your feet right underneath your
left shoulder. You could come
onto your fingertips if the
ground was easier to retrieve
that way. And then bend through
your left knee straight into the
right leg and press the left
hand or fingertips into the
ground. Inhale, pull your
shoulders away from your ears.
And exhale, twist towards the
right extending the right arm
up. Inhale here And exhale,
change sides. Right hand comes
down a foot length ahead and in
between your feet right
underneath your right shoulder.
Right knees bent, left leg is
straight, pressing the right
hand or fingertips into the
ground. Then reach out through
your left hand. Pull your
shoulders away from the ears,
take another deep breath. And
then come down, letting yourself
hang. On your next inhale, walk
your feet back, set your knees
down and come to sit on your
heels. You want to make sure
that you're comfortable here.
You'll stay here for a bit. So
feel free to press pause and
change your seat in any way that
you need to.
And then lift up through your
right arm, right shoulder stays
down, holding the right
fingertips up to the ceiling.
Take a deep inhale here,
engaging through your core.
Continually reaching up through
those fingertips. And then as
you exhale, place your right
hand between your shoulder
blades. You could take all that
space here. I really liked how
the skin feels in that area. So
maybe you can enjoy that. And
grab a hold of your right elbow
with your left hand gently
pulling the right elbow to
center shoulders stay low.
Inhale, reach to your heart,
reach to the crown of your head.
And then as you exhale, extend
the left arm to the side,
rotating the palm back and then
up. And now grab a hold of your
T shirt or another piece of
clothing or if it's available to
you your hand. It's important
that you establish tension here.
Then you're going to take three
breaths, keep reaching through
the heart and pulling down
through the shoulders gently
leaning back in your upper back.
Soft face and strong core. Then
on your fourth inhale, very
slowly returned to center.
Bringing your arms into that T
shape again and rotating your
palms up and down, sharing some
love with your shoulders. And
then let's change sides when
you're ready to take your time.
Then you're going to lift up
through your left arm, your left
shoulder stays down, pulling the
left fingertips up to the
ceiling. Take an inhale here
engaging through the core. And
then as you exhale, place your
left hand between your shoulder
blades. Again, greeting that
space, Hello. Then grab a hold
of your left elbow with your
right hand. gently pulling the
left elbow to center shoulders
stay low. Inhale, reach through
your heart, reach to the crown
of your head. Exhale, gently
pull that elbow and then extend
the right arm to the side again
rotating the palm at first back
and then up and then grab a hold
on your T shirt or another piece
of clothing or if available your
hand. respect your boundaries
further isn't better. It's just
different. Then you're gonna
take three deep breaths,
reaching up through the heart
pulling down to the shoulders
again, you could start gently
leaning back in the upper back.
Keep engaging to the core then
on your fourth inhale slowly
return to center. Bring your
arms into that T shape again and
rotate your palms up and down
sharing some love with your
shoulders.
And then from here I will meet
you in plank pose so your hands
come down shoulder width apart
directly underneath your
shoulders. Your fingers are
spreading why and the knuckles
of your hands pressed down. Your
feet are hips width apart and
you have one long line from your
heels all the way to the crown
of your head. And then release
your knees to the ground. Come
onto your forearms, slowly
lowering the legs and the pelvis
down and tuck your toes your
feet or hips width apart or
wider To make sure that you have
a right angle in your elbow
joints, elbows placed directly
underneath your shoulders. Check
if you're able to grab a hold of
opposite elbows here and then
bring your forearms down, hands
parallel to your elbows. And
it's important here to keep on
pressing your wrists down and at
the same time pulling your
elbows towards your upper body,
without that being visible, just
noticeable for you. Engage to
your legs, press your big
toenails down, pull your pubic
bone to your belly button. Then
pull your shoulders back away
from your ears. take three deep
breaths, reaching forward
through your heart and back
through your shoulders. Keep
engaging the core. Keep
activating the legs. On your
third exhale, slowly release the
upper body and extend the right
arm forward. slowly rolling over
your right side come onto your
back and then walk your feet as
close to the pelvis as possible.
Make sure that your feet are
hips with apart. Your toes are
facing forward and your knees or
hips width apart to So feet and
knees are parallel that is
really important. And then from
here, lifting the pelvis began
to roll up one vertebra at a
time. coming towards bridge
pose. You could place your arms
parallel to each other
underneath your back or
interlace your fingers if
available to you. Rotate your
shoulders towards one another
creating a pillow for your neck
here. And take three more deep
breaths. Pressing your feet down
activating your legs with every
inhale.
with every exhale pulling your
sternum to your chin opening the
chest deep breaths don't let
your knees fall out here. On
your fourth inhale, release your
hands and one vertebra at a time
roll down as slowly as possible.
Really take your time here. and
once you're all the way down,
you are going to bring your feet
as wide as the mat let your
knees fall in towards one
another. And giving the lower
back permission to sink. Take a
deep inhale in through your nose
and exhale out the mouth, hahhhhh
Soften the shoulders, let the
head be heavy. then bring your
knees into your chest, grab a
hold of each knee with the
respective hand and breathe into
your hips here. Lower back stays
level shoulders stay on the
ground and when you're ready,
extend arms and legs coming into
final relaxation pose eyes
falling close releasing the
weight of your body and to the
ground. So some say that this is
the most important pose in yoga.
If you have time, I encourage
you to press pause and take a
good long rest here.
When you're ready, start to
deepen your breath, hugging your
knees into your chest, rolling
over to the right. Pressing your
left hand down and coming to
sit. Take it slow, take your
time and hug your knees into
your chest. wrap your arms
around your knees and rest your
forehead on your knees eyes are
closed. Give yourself a hug
after class here hugging and
everything that makes you you
today. Not tomorrow. Not last
year. The right here right now.
And then release In your hands
to your heart take an inhale and
exhale.
Thank you so much, and I wish a
beautiful day and I hope to see
you on the mat again soon.
Namaste